<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fire's continued at Oxford, or, The decree of the convocation for burning the Naked gospel, considered in a letter to a person of honour</title>
            <author>Parkinson, James, 1653-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11875697</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11875697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50224</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56411)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50224)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 504:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fire's continued at Oxford, or, The decree of the convocation for burning the Naked gospel, considered in a letter to a person of honour</title>
                  <author>Parkinson, James, 1653-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated, p. 14: Aug. 30, 1690.</note>
                  <note>"The naked gospel" was written by Arthur Bury.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. 15.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bury, Arthur, 1624-1713. --  Naked Gospel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50224:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50224:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The FIRE's continued at</hi> OXFORD: OR, The Decree of the Convocation for burning
<hi>the Naked Goſpel,</hi> conſidered.</head>
            <head type="sub">In a Letter to a Perſon of Honour.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Gave you in my laſt the ſtate of the Controverſy between the Bp. of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and
the Rector and major part of the Fellows of <hi>Exeter</hi>-Colledg at <hi>Oxford,</hi> as well as
I could collect it from the Relations I could meet with, and from their Petition to her Majeſty,
before whom the Cauſe is depending. In the mean time, the <hi>Gazette</hi> will inform you, The
Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in Convocation held, <hi>Aug.</hi> 19. inſtant, has paſt their
Judgment and Decree againſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Propoſitions as Impious and Heretical, cited out of a
certain infamous Libel— entituled, <hi>The Naked Goſpel,</hi> which (ſay they) impugn and
deſtroy the chief Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our Faith, always held and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Catholick Church,
and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the Engliſh. And in the Preface to their Decree, they ſay, it not only
denies, but expoſes to ſcorn that very Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is God bleſſed for
ever.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, before I take into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the impious and heretical Propoſitions, give me
leave to give you a ſhort Summary of the Tendency and Deſign of the Book, and of the reputed
Author's printing it at his own Charge, as I am inform'd by ſome that know him, for I do not know
him my ſelf, nor ever had any communication with him.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the Author's Deſign in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it. When the King had called a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to
reconcile (as was hoped) to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the ſeveral Parties in this Kingdom,
and to ſatisfy (if poſſible) the Conſciences of thoſe who differ from it, this Author was
willing to contribute to ſo good a Work. But becauſe a direct Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs might appear too great
a boldneſs (as ſome that went that way afterward found) he conceiv'd that a clear ſtating the
firſt Principles of the Goſpel, would appear more ſuitable to ſo learned a Body, and
uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful toward enlargement of the Mind to a comprehenſive Charity. He therefore got this
Treatiſe printed, with deſign to ſteal a Copy of it into the Hand of every Member of the
Convocation, without publiſhing it to the World. No ſooner was the Impreſſion finiſhed,
but he found the Hopes of the King, and the Generality of good Men diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50224:2"/>by the rigour of the prevailing Party in the Convocation; and a great Noiſe
made about this well-deſign'd Book, whereof ſome ſew Copies had gotten abroad. The Author
hereupon made ſome Changes in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Book, leaving out ſuch Paſſages as
appeared moſt offenſive; and of this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion he communicated more Copies than he had
done of the former. But now cometh out a ſtolen Impreſſion of the firſt Book, made at
<hi>London,</hi> by he knows not whom, which put it out of his power to diſpoſe as he pleas'd,
of a Book that was his own.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Writing, and then by Printing and Altering, wholly at his own Coſt. Thus it
appears his Deſign was not to diſturb the Peace of the Church, but to promote it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Deſign and Tendency of the Book, I will preſume to whiſper to you, (out of
hearing of the Convocation) is ſuch, as partly by reconciling Controverſies, partly by
diſtinguiſhing neceſtary Articles from thoſe that are not neceſſary, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off
Diſputes about the Modes and Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of things in groſs neceſſary; by giving ſuch a
Scheme of Chriſtian Religion as is clear and plain to vulgar Capacities, and apt to remove
Doubts, and Fears, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties, and to ſatisfy good Peoples Minds touching their being in
the true way of Salvation, notwithſtanding the many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and Diſputes among
conſcientious Men, which they are either not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, or not with full ſatisfattion
to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; to turn Mens Minds from the ſtudy of Opinions, and Speculations, to Practical
Piety, Devotion toward God and Chriſt, and Love toward all Chriſtians of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions;
in the mean time making Rents and Diviſions, Heats and Animoſities about Matters hardly
determinable, to be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and unbecoming ſincere Chriſtians. This Book, I ſay, having
this Deſign and Tendency, were not People prejudiced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it by raſh and preſumptuous
Decrees and Cenſures, might be of as great benefit to the. World in general, and the Chriſtian
World in ſpecial, as perhaps any Book of that Subject that has been publiſh'd theſe hundred
Years. When you have read the Book, I doubt not but you will be of my Mind. But for all that, I
could have wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Author had not, by ſome elegant Figures of Speech, either bordered upon
Hyperbole's, or made his Mind leſs intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible to common Readers, and laid himſelf more open
to the Cavils of his fierce Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, (which he did not fear among ſo learned Men as our
Convocation.)</p>
            <p>For, except the manner of expreſſion, I make no queſtion but your own Memory will
ſuggeſt to you, that (as we ſay of the Holy Scriptures, they contain in one Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle all
thoſe excellent Precepts and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which lie diſpers'd, ſome in one, ſome in
another of the Philoſophers) ſo die <hi>Naked Goſpel</hi> contains nothing but what is found
by Parcels, in other eminent and allowed Authors, whom the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation dare not
paſs Sentence upon, tho' they have appear'd of late Years preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous enough in that kind;
witneſs their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Judgment and Decree paſt in Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>July</hi> 21. 1683.
declaring 27 Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions <hi>to be Falſe, Seditious, and Impious; and moſt of them to be
alſo Heretical and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, infamous to Chriſtian Religion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to all
Government in Church and State.</hi> And this at ſuch a time, when the Court ſollicited that
Judgment for promoting their horrid Deſign of introducing Popery and Arbitrary Government into
theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and rooting that peſtilent Hereſy of Proteſtantiſm out of all Nations;
to which that <hi>Oxford</hi>-Decree was greatly ſerviceable. And had the Body of the People of
<hi>England</hi> been throughly perſwaded of the Truth, Equity, and Religion of that Decree in
all the Propoſitions, we could never have had the happy cauſe of bleſſing God for
deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us from French Tyranny, and Popiſh Cruelty and Superſtition, by the glorious
Courage and Conduct of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> nor could the Peers, and
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of the Nation in Convention,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50224:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>have ſett'd the Crown upon their moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſties,
<hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi> but we had in all likelyhood been for ever enſlaved to a
bigotted Popiſh King, and the Lady of <hi>Loretto</hi>'s Heirs. For it is obſervable, that the
Vote of the Convention, which decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red K. <hi>James</hi>'s Throne vacant, was grounded upon his
having broken the Contract between King and People. And that there is ſuch a Contract, is the
Propoſition condemned as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious by the ſame Hand which now condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>N. G.</hi> At
this time we ſee that thoſe Biſhops, and others, that have through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly digeſted the
<hi>Oxford</hi>-Principles of Paſſive Obedience, and Non-reſiſtanne, can rather loſe
their Preferments, than ſwear Allegiance to our King and Queen. And ſince divers of the Clergy
profeſs to ſwear to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties as King and Queen <hi>de Facto</hi> only; Have we not
reaſonable grounds to ſuſpect the Paſſive-Obedience-men of the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be ſuch?
And perhaps our Author may have ſomewhat more incurr'd their Enmity by his being (as I hear he
is) a <hi>de Jure</hi> Liege-man, and did not join his Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in that Decree.</p>
            <p>This burning Decree of the Convocation of <hi>Oxford, July</hi> 21. — 83. brings freſh
to my Mind the moſt unjuſt Expulſion of Mr. <hi>Parkinſon</hi> from that Univerſity, and
conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently from his Fellowſhip in <hi>Lincoln</hi>-Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, whereby, and from his Pupils,
he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd about 120 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum;</hi> of all which he was depriv'd, without
any Trial, about the very time of that Convocation, and for holding (as was pretended) ſome of
thoſe Propoſitions condemned by that Decree; and whilſt he ſtood indicted for the ſame at
the Aſſizes of <hi>Oxford,</hi> where, and at the King's-Bench <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> he was
forced to give attendance for about three Years. And tho' he has been reſtor'd to the Liberty of
the Univerſity, by the late Vice-Chancellor, now Biſhop of <hi>Briſtol;</hi> yet to this Day
he cannot procure reſtoration to his Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, much leſs reparation of his great Damages
ſuſtain'd in the ſpace of full ſeven Years. How does Dr. <hi>H</hi>—'s Conſcience
ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to ſleep while it is not done, ſince he was the chief Agent in that
Expulſion!</p>
            <p>Let me enquire now how theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men-burners make good their Sentence, That <hi>the Naked
Goſpel plucks up by the Roots the Primitive Doctrine once delivered to the Saints; deſtroys the
chief Myſteries of our Religion; and not only denies, but expoſes to ſcorn that very Jeſus
Chriſt our Lord, who bought us, and who is God bleſſed for ever.</hi> A heavy Charge indeed,
and which is to be abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all Chriſtians. But what ſhall we ſay of theſe Judges if
they fail in their Proofs? muſt they not fall under the Character of falſe Accuſers, and
unjuſt Judges?</p>
            <p>The Matters contain'd in the Book, from firſt to laſt, ſhew plainly, that the Author is
neither <hi>Arian</hi> nor <hi>Socinian;</hi> for he is ſo far from denying even the Eternal
Divinity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that he plainly enough confeſſes it; but if he both
confeſſes it and denies it, he contradicts himſelf, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid abſolutely either
to confeſs or deny it. But that he confeſſes it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies only the neceſſity of
underſtanding and believing the manner of it, appears in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Paſſages, (which is one main
diſtinction which the Learned Judges ought to have conſidered.) As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 24. <hi>Iſt</hi> Edit. <hi>The ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite,
abſolute, implicit Belief, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged due to God, is alſo due to Chriſt:</hi>
Which could not be ſaid by one that did not believe him an Infinite God.</p>
            <p>Again, 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>Other Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters ſpeak an unmeaſurable
Excellency: but this [the only begotten Son of God] ſpeaks an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable One.</hi> And a few
Lines after he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, That <hi>the Divinity of our Lord maketh the Dignity of his Perſon
unintelligible, and for that very reaſon he is to be believed in with utmoſt confidence.</hi>
P. 37.</p>
            <p>Then conſider, 3. what he affirmeth <hi>Pag.</hi> 39. that our Saviour in anſwering the
Jews, who were offended at him for having ſtiled himſelf the Son of God, <hi>did not upon ſo
preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing occaſion aſſert his right, but abating ſo much as exceeded their
comprehenſion</hi> — <hi>ſpeaks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50224:3"/>of what he had been from Eternity in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but what he was in relation to
the World, and in compariſon with other Meſſengers of God to it.</hi> — <hi>Thus did
he</hi> (<hi>like</hi> Elijah) <hi>contract himſelf to their Dimenſions, requiring only ſuch
a meaſure of Faith, as was ſuitable to their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings and his own Deſigns.</hi>
Here the Author, ſaying that our Lord did not aſſert his Right, muſt mean his Right to that
Title, which the Jews accus'd him of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my for uſurping, (which was, that he being a Man,
made himſelf God) clearly ſuppoſes him to be God. And again, in ſaying, he ſpake nothing
<hi>of what he was from Eternity in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> He ſuppoſeth it was a Truth beyond
controverſy, that he was from Eternity; and that ſo much the more plainly, becauſe it comes
as part of a Diſcourſe, which ſhews that our Lord did not aſſert his Right.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What the Burners produce as Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal in evidence of their Charge, <hi>viz.</hi> That
<hi>his Generation muſt needs be-ſo much above our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, as the Nature of God is
above our own;</hi> may much more juſtly be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in defence of the Author, as a proof that
he believed, our. Lord's Divinity, than be objected as ſubverting the Faith of it.</p>
            <p>Since therefore he acknowledged our. Lord's Divinity for a Truth, as we ſee; the
Propoſitions the Burners cite as denying it, muſt be as clear as theſe; or elſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
does not contradict himſelf, but muſt be reckon'd Orthodox in the Faith. For ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure
Paſſages ought in reaſon to be expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by thoſe that are clear; And then the Burners
fall ſhort in proving their heinous Charge; and all the Fault of the Author muſt lie in his
denying it to be a matter of neceſſary ſaving-Faith. But the great Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of the
Catholick Doctrine were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally guilty of the ſame Hereſy. St. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> wrote no
leſs than twelve Books con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Trinity, yet in the cloſe of the 10th hath theſe
words, <hi>Non per difficiles nos Deus ad beatam vitam queſtiones vocat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>God
doth not call us to a bleſſed. Life by difficult. Queſtions, nor ſolicites us by a manifold
kind of Eloquence;</hi> the way of <hi>Eternity is plain and eaſy to us;</hi> viz. <hi>To believe
that God-raiſed Jeſus from the Dead, and to confeſs him our Lord.</hi> In which words we
ſee, not only in the preſent Queſtion concerning our Lord's. Perſon, but in all others, how
little of mere Belief is required to Salvation. Nor do we find the leaſt Hint to the contrary in
the Hiſtory of thoſe Times, wherein the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy raged; tho' they Perſecuted one
another, they did not Damn one another; they contended for their Opinions, as for great Truths,
wherein our Lord's Honour was concern'd, not as for Articles of Faith, whereon the Believer's
Salvation depended. Sr. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays, <hi>All Neceſſaries are clear and
manifeſt.</hi> And <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> after thirteen Years ſtudy, calls them <hi>Fools</hi>
who too curiouſly enquire into the Incarnation of our Lord.</p>
            <p>Yea, and thoſe who were ſo eager for condemning the <hi>Naked Goſpel</hi> to the Flames,
cannot ſure but think it more diſhonourable to the Saviour of the World, to believe he will
damn any Man for failing of ſo difficult a Truth, when he ſincerely believes the clear.
Goſpel, than any other Error concerning the Divinity of his Perſon can be.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Diſtinction which the Author might juſlly have expected from ſuch Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Perſons, was, That the Queſtion in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate was not concerning the Divinity, or mere Humanity of
our Lord's Perſon, but concerning a Nicety ſo inconſiderable, that neither the Emperor nor a
Council could find the difference between the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Arian</hi> Confeſſion.
And doubtleſs it muſt be ſomething worſe than Inadvertency that can blind any Man ſo far,
as to diſable him from diſcovering, that from the beginning of the 7th Chapter to the 10th,
this Author ſpeaketh only as a Commentator upon the. Letter of the great Emperor
<hi>Conſtantine,</hi> wherein he equally condemneth both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for troubling the Peace of his
Empire with ſuch a Queſtion, wherein it was not diſputed whether Chriſt were God or not,
(for therein both ſides agreed) but in what manner, he was begotten, or wherein he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed or
differ'd from the Father.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:50224:3"/>
            <p>There is a Paſſage which I find in the laſt Impreſſion, (which perhaps is not in many
Hands, and little notice taken of it) in which the Author, by cloſing that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
diſplayeth his meaning in it, which though it be ſomewhat long, I think fit to
tranſcribe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag,</hi> 48, 49. [AND what is all this to BELIEVING IN CHRIST? Yea, what is it to the
PERSON of Chriſt? Had freedom from Perſecution, ſuffered a Controverſy to have ſprung
three or four Ages before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſome that then <hi>believed Chriſt to be God, and others
that believed Jeſus to be the Chriſt, but a Man born of Men,</hi> (as we heard from
<hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>); the importance of ſuch a Controverſy would have juſtified the Heat
wherewith it ſhould be perſecuted. But here it was quite otherwiſe: The Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at
firſt appeared very ſlight, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward none at all: For the Confeſſion of
<hi>Arius</hi> after his condemnation was ſo like the <hi>Nicene,</hi> that neither the Emperor
himſelf, nor a Council, found any defect in it. The angry Biſhop indeed found a word wanting,
but ſuch a word as proved too unweildy, even for thoſe who would not diſpence with it. This
word <hi>Arius</hi> omitted as no leſs need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs than intractable: But he and his followers
acknowledged Chriſt to be <hi>the only begotten Son of God, begotten before all Worlds, God of
God, Light of Light, very God of very God:</hi> Was not this ſo believe in him? Is it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to believe, that as he created the World, ſo he governeth it? that as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
everlaſting Life to his Believers, ſo he is able to perform it? that he now ſeeth, and will
hereafter reward every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Works? Doth not this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all the Deſigns of
Faith, Love, Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, Obedience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Can none be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers but
Metaphyſicians only? Nor all they neither, but only ſuch as fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the new-coin'd
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and can ſo nicely apply them to the Perſon of
Chriſt, as to ſalve all Difficulties? The Parties themſelves did not think ſo. The leading
Biſhops, in the midſt of their. Heats allowed Toleration to the Diſſenters, and all of both
ſides during the Perſecution under <hi>Julian,</hi> communicated in die ſame Churches, and in
all good Offices, both of Devotion toward God, and Charity toward each other; they mutually
comforted and ſtrengthned one another in defence of the Chriſtian Faith: By this it appeareth,
they did not judg one another to be Infidels, and conſequently, that the Faith to which Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Life is promiſed, was not concern'd in the Controverſy.</p>
            <p>An Evidence concurring with greater, to prove that the Creed which weareth the Name of
<hi>Athanaſius,</hi> was not his Iſſue nor Contemporary. And where is that
Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Man, who doth not ſo diſtinguiſh the Doctrines of that Creed from
its Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, as to retain the former in their full import, but pull out the String of the
latter, by ſuch an Interpretation as leaves uncan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell'd our Saviour's Patent of Eternal Life to
whoſoever believeth in him?]</p>
            <p>Theſe are the words of the Author, wherein he ſummeth up the Deſign of all he had ſaid
concerning Faith toward the Perſon of Chriſt, and whereby are rendred inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any that
charge him with <hi>Arianiſm, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm,</hi> or any other hard Character.</p>
            <p>No! his Hereſy lay not in the Book, but the Concluſion. The Concluſion was ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky,
as not only to contradict the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, but the very Speech of thoſe Leaders of that
Convocation. In the days of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. the Biſhops moved the Temporal Lords to ſuit the
Law of <hi>England</hi> to the Canon Law, by legitimating Children born before Wedlock: The
Temporal Lords anſwered, <hi>Nolumus L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges
Augliae mutari, quia huc uſque uſu approbatae ſunt.</hi> The former half of theſe words,
the Noble Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> took for the Motto of his Standard, wherein there was neither
need nor place for the later half; and it is well known, who with equal Wit, Wiſdom, and
Gratitude; threw it in his Face in that Convocation. Could any thing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50224:4"/>more provoke ſuch a Man's ſpleen, than a Diſcourſe ſo croſs, both to
the Determination and the Reaſon, as for this very Reaſon to prove a Change ought to be made,
becauſe Experience had proved thoſe Laws unhappy in ſucceeding Ages, which were wiſely and
charitably inſtituted, for that Age wherein they were firſt eſtabliſhed? This was an
Affront never to be digeſted, but for its ſake the whole Book muſt be condemned, and the
Author proſecuted.</p>
            <p>From this general Apology for the Author's Innocency, I will now proceed to take a ſhort view
of the particular Propoſitions, whereby the Burners prove the equity of their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and
Execution.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'That <hi>Mahomet</hi> profeſs'd all the Articles of the Chriſtian
Faith.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the firſt ſtep we may ſee whither they are going. They quote the Words
of the Author, as the Devil did Scripture, by halves: Had they gone on, as a Faithful Witneſs
ſhould do, it muſt plainly appear that the Author meant not to equal <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met's</hi> Belief
with the Chriſtians, but to ſhew the Deſign and Succeſs of his Pretences: For thus he
proceeds,
<q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Mahomet</hi> profeſt all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith,
and declared himſelf, not an Apoſtate, but Reformer: pretending to purify it from the
Corruption wherewith it had be'n defiled, and perfect it with Additionals; he framed ſuch a
Jargon, as appeared moſt ſerviceable to his Ends, and moſt ſuitable to his Luſt.</q> And
ſure their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice muſt have be'n too hard for their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory if they had forgotten what had
be'n ſaid,
<q rend="margQuotes">'That the Author of the <hi>Alcoran</hi> was no other than a leud
brain-ſick Scoundrel, and his Doctrines (as far as they are his) no better than extravagant
Whimſies, or leud Panders to Luſt. And again, that the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches had their
Candleſtick removed by the Sword of a baſe Slave and his few Followers, and by Doctrines weak
as That Sword when firſt unſheathed, and leud as thoſe Rogues that managed it.</q> But alas!
this would have ſpoil'd the firſt moſt Heretical and Impious Propoſition, and the Author
muſt have ſcap't without that ſevere Character of being a Friend to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and a
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> which any one will think him to be with a Witneſs, who ſhall
read this ſo <hi>juſt</hi> Decree, and never view the. Book it ſelf: Do you not bluſh, Sir,
at the Ingenuity of that Perſon who drew out this abominable Propoſition? And are you not
almoſt afraid, that the Learned Condemners took it upon truſt, without too laborious an
Examination?</p>
            <p>And ſo much for this ſtrong, firm and laudable Foundation. Let us proceed to the reſt of
the Blaſphemies.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Pref.</hi> Whether <hi>Mahomet</hi> or Chriſtian Doctors have more
corrupted the Goſpel, is not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo plain by the Light of Scripture, as it is by that of
Experience, that the later gave Occaſion, Encouragement and Advantage to the former. For when by
nice and hot Diſputes (eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Second and Third Perſons of the Trinity)
the Minds of the whole Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had bin long confounded, and by the then late Eſtabliſhment of
Image-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the Scandal was encreaſed, ſo that to vulgar underſtandings the Doctrine of
the Trinity appeared no leſs guilty of Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm, than that of Image-Worſhip did of
Idolatry—Then was there a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting opportunity offered to the Impoſtor, and he laid hold
on it, to ſet up himſelf for a Reformer of ſuch Corruptions, as were both too groſs to be
Juſtified, and too viſible to be Denied.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Chriſtian Doctors had not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Time, ſo far
corrupted the Goſpel as they have done ſince: But their then late eſtabliſhment of
Image-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, gave ſuch ſcandal to the vulgar rude <hi>Arabians,</hi> that the Idolatry
which was viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble therein, made them infer, that thoſe who were ſo guilty thereof, were no
leſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50224:4"/>guilty of Polytheiſm in the Doctrine of the Trinity, which to this Day they
ſtill believe. But where doth the denial of Chriſt's God-head appear in all this?</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 40. The great Queſtion concerning the
God-Head of Chriſt is, 1. Impertinent to our Lord's Deſign. 2. Fruitleſs to the Contemplators
own pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. 3. Dangerous.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The great Queſtion was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Godhead of Chriſt,</hi> (for
therein both Parties agreed) but concerning the <hi>Eternity of his Godhead.</hi> They both held he
was before the World, and made the World. Judges in Criminal Matters ſhould not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the
Evidence. And whatever the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſpeaketh of that Queſtion, is by way of Gloſs upon the
Great <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Letter, never yet judged Heretical, (as I obſerv'd before.) Is
here a Tittle of the Author's denying the Godhead of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 46. Two Evangeliſts trace our Lord's
Genealogy; but as they derive it not from his real, but ſuppoſed Father, ſo do they take two
ſeveral ways, not to ſatisfy, but to amuſe us. What is this but to admoniſh us againſt
Curioſity? The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree of his Fleſh might eaſily have bin, either cleared or unmentioned;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad the Evangeliſts bin wholly ſilent
concerning it, We had leſs wondred; but that they ſhould profeſs to inſtruct us, yet doubly
diſappoint us, firſt by deriving it from a wrong Father, and then by diſtracting us between
two ways; what is this but to verify the Propher's Deſcription, <hi>Who ſhall declare his
Generation?</hi> and what doth this ſo careful concealment of his Generation according to his
Humane Nature ſignify more plainly, than a warning againſt ſearching after the Eternal
Generation of his Divinity? If it were needleſs (and therefore left impoſſible) to prove him
derived from <hi>David,</hi> which was one of his moſt revealed Characters; How can it be
otherwiſe, to underſtand that Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of his, which muſt needs be ſo much the more
above our Underſtanding, as the Nature of God is above our own?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Matter of Fact is plain: Our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſhew us, that the two Evangeliſts
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive our Lord's Pedigree from his reputed Father, and that they proceed therein two ſeveral
ways: The Inference is innocent, <hi>What doth this ſo careful concealment of his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,
according to his Humane Nature, ſignify more plainly, than a warning againſt ſearching after
the eternal Generation of his Divinity</hi> — <hi>which muſt be ſo much the more above
our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, as the Nature of God is above our own.</hi> Here again the eternal
Generation of his Divinity is plainly ſuppos'd, ſo far are they from proving the denial of
it.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Pag.</hi> 48. And might not a Heathen at this rate juſtify
Polytheiſm, provided his Gods diſagreed not amongſt themſelves? The Schoolmen therefore
will not ſtand to this State of the Queſtion, but diſtinguiſh between <hi>Perſon,</hi>
and <hi>Suppoſitum rationale;</hi> which yet they cannot ſo do, as to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy themſelves,
and therefore ſhelter themſelves in their impregnable Fort, <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and thence
thunder upon the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries both of this, and of another no leſs beloved <hi>Myſtery:</hi>
For they make this their Cock-argument for Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation; That ſince the Scripture is
no leſs expreſs for the One than the Other, and the Contradictions no leſs groſs in the One
than in the Other; therefore we muſt embrace the One as well as the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'To this Objection of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and to others of the
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitaries,</hi> we have found an Anſwer, That we muſt not infer from our Own Nature to
God's; for that Ours is finite, and God's is infinite; Three Perſons among us are Three Men,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they agree in one Common Nature; but the Divine Nature is not a Common One, but a
Singular; and therefore Three Perſons do not make Three Gods. If you underſtand not this, you
muſt not wonder,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50224:5"/>or at leaſt you muſt not Gainſay it; for it is a Myſtery, which Reaſon
may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to fathom.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Cenſurer underſtood well how to ſtop ſhort; for had he gone one
Line further, he had diſcovered the Innocency of the Author's Intentions; the Words are, <hi>Why
if it be a Myſtery, and muſt ſtill be ſo, to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe do we enquire into it, or
diſpute concerning it?</hi> which plainly ſhew he did not intend either to Aſſert or Deny
either ſide of the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but ſet aſide the whole as not to be Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and
therefore not to be Diſputed. Theſe Words are not in the Author's Second Impreſſion; ſo
unwilling was he (it ſeems) to diſpleaſe, that he was at a great charge to have theſe and
other things left out. But how juſtifiable are they even in the firſt? for they follow
<hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s way of ſtating the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which was, That <hi>Peter, James</hi> and
<hi>John are not three Men if they be of one Mind, becauſe then they are one in the Lord.</hi>
And doth it not thence clearly follow, that a Heathen might at the ſame rate juſtify
Polytheiſm, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided his Gods diſagreed not among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? But who knows not that the
School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Moderns do generally (as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſays) reject that way of Arguing, as indeed
introducing three Gods, one <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> but three in number?</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Pag.</hi> 51. Thus have we pointed (and only pointed) at ſome of
the many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangling Queſtions, which puzzeled, and divided the ſubtileſt Wits of ſeveral
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and were at laſt decided by no other Evidence, but of Imperial and Papal Authority;
ſufficient to ſilence Diſputes, but not ſtabliſh Truth. And who is he that is not
diſcouraged from giving a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Aſſent to what is this way obtruded upon his
Belief?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is not in the Second Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; if it were, where is the Hereſy of
it? Matter of Fact appears in the Hiſtorians; and the Inference, <hi>Who is he that is not
diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged from giving a confident aſſent to what is this way obtruded upon his
Belief?</hi> What conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Man would not ask the fame Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion?</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>pag.</hi> 53. I. There is danger of Blaſphemy in
Examining the <hi>Silly</hi> Queſtion <hi>(as he calls it)</hi> concerning the Eternity of the
Godhead of Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's call'd a <hi>Silly Queſtion,</hi> in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s
Letter which calls it <hi>Silly;</hi> ſome of whoſe Words are cited immediately
before—<hi>We ought</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to reſtrain our ſelves from talking, leſt when
we cannot ſufficiently explain the Queſtion, or our Hearers cannot ſufficiently underſtand
our meaning; either way the People be driven upon a neceſſity of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy or
Contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ib.</hi> 53.
<q rend="margQuotes">'This is a ſecond Danger, That we have <hi>no firm ground</hi> to go
upon.—</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is not in the Second Impreſſion. But did not the Author give ſufficient Reaſons for
it? <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>all are challenged by either Party with equal aſſurance. Scriptures,
Antiquity, and Councils too, as the Emperors chanced to influence them.</hi> Does not Biſhop
<hi>Taylor</hi> ſay as much? <hi>Liberty of Proph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Pag.</hi> 54. The only advantage of the Catholicks is long
Poſſeſſion, and that after Sentence—They have indeed ſo handled matters, as to hide
much, and varniſh all; yet even ſo we may pick out enough to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify an Appeal, by
obſerving how that Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion was firſt obtained, then continued, and at laſt
ſetled—The Sentence which firſt determined the Controverſy <hi>[in the Council of
Nice]</hi> was not by the merit of the Cauſe, but Intereſt of the Parties.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This alſo is not in the Second Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. And why, if the Sentence
which firſt determin'd the Controverſy [in the Council of <hi>Nice</hi>] was, by the Merit of
the Cauſe, and not by the Intereſt of the Parties: Why did the Catholicks in after-Ages, and at
this Day, impoſe another ſenſe upon the <hi>Nicene</hi> Sentence, than what was manifeſtly
their meaning? What is this, but to make a Noſe of Wax of that Council, as the Papiſts do of
Scripture?</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50224:5"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Pag.</hi> 56. This long and miſchievous Controverſy was at
laſt ſettled by <hi>Theodoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> who having received his Inſtructions and Baptiſm
from a Conſubſtantialiſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired all his Subjects to conform to that Religion, which
<hi>Peter</hi> the Prince of the Apoſtles from the beginning had delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Romans, and
which at that time <hi>Damaſus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Alexandria</hi> held; and that Church only ſhould be eſteemed Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick which worſhipped
the Divine Trinity with equal Honour; and thoſe which held the other ſhould be called
Hereticks, made Infamous, and Puniſhed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'This therefore we may call ſetling the Controverſy; becauſe
thenceforth all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Emperors, and Biſhops wrote after this Copy, and both the Parties
have ever worn theſe Titles, which the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror by his Imperial Power, as the unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable
Fountain of Honour, was pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to beſtow upon them.—Behold now the Ground upon which
one of our Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Articles of Faith is built; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Juſtice of that Plea, which from
ſuch a poſſeſſion would preſcribe to our Belief.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is not in the Second Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. As it is in the Firſt, the
Hiſtorian that affirms it, is to anſwer for it, and not our Author. As for thoſe
words—<hi>Behold now the Ground upon which one of our Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Articles of Faith is
built; behold the Juſtice of that Plea, which from ſuch a poſſeſſion would preſcribe
to our Belief.</hi> I know not what that Author would ſay to it; but I ſay, that the Catholicks
do, by receding from the Senſe of thoſe Ages in that Article, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg it to be weakly
grounded.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Pag.</hi> 57. <hi>of the Interpolated Edition.</hi> What more
ridiculouſly ſilly than to build ſo weighty a Doctrine upon Implicit Faith in two Biſhops,
partial to their own Sees, whereof the One gave it Birth, and the Other Maintenance? and what more
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious than to proſecute as Hereticks and Malefactors, all ſuch as ſhould refuſe to be
ſo groſly impoſed upon?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is plainly to be underſtood of the Doctrine controverted in thoſe
Times, as impos'd on us as neceſſary to Salvation, to be believed in a modern and
unintelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Senſe, though in old equivocal Terms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 57. <hi>of the firſt Edition.</hi> Certainly
<q rend="margQuotes">'whoſoever ſhall carefully obſerve how the now eſtabliſhed
Doctrine was from firſt to laſt advanced by groſs partiality of the moſt guilty kind, and
at laſt impoſed by a Novice <hi>Emperor,</hi> upon Implicit Faith of two Biſhops, of whoſe
Sees, the one brought it into the World, and the other maintain'd it, and a new coin'd Tradition
lately obtruded by the guiltier of thoſe Sees, but unpleaded, becauſe, unheard of in thoſe
former, long and miſerable times, which it might, and ought to have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the
Convulſions they ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: Whoever, I ſay, ſhall Carefully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this, and withal
what foul Tricks the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> uſed in the Weſt, and with what ill Succeſs in
the Eaſt, whoſe Churches did at laſt more Univerſally em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace <hi>Arius</hi>'s Opinion,
than at firſt they condemned it; may be tempted to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> among the
Roman Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and cannot but think it fairly dealt with, if (its boaſted Poſſeſſion
pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) it be left upon the ſame level with the <hi>Arian,</hi> equally unworthy not only of
our Faith, but of our Study.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſame Anſwer I gave to the former will ſerve to this: Is it not equal
that thoſe Doctrines, whether <hi>Arian</hi> or <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſian,</hi> that conſiſt of
infinite Subtilities and Niceties, which the common Chriſtians never could nor can underſtand,
which have been conceiv'd, brought forth and nurſed in ſuch a way of Policy, Ambition, and
Perſecution, as Hiſtories inform us: Is it not equal they ſhould be left upon the ſame
Level, equally unworthy, not only of the Faith, but alſo of the Study of thoſe that heartily
believe whatſoever they find in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50224:6"/>Holy Scriptures? plain Things in the plain Senſe, and obſcure Texts in the
beſt Senſe they can, in conſonancy to plain and clear Ones.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Pag.</hi> 57. If further we conſider (what the Hiſtorian
expreſly declareth) that at the riſe of this Controverſy, moſt of the Biſhops
underſtood not it's meaning, we cannot think it neceſſary to Salvation, that every private
Chriſtian ſhould believe that as an Article of Faith, which the beſt Ages of the Church
thought no worth knowing —[<hi>This upon ſecond thoughts is thus expreſs'd in a</hi> 2d
<hi>Edition.</hi> An Opinion which ſo many <hi>wiſe and good</hi> Men as lived within 300 Years
after Chriſt, were ſo far from believing matter of <hi>Faith,</hi> that they did not receive it
as matter of <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty,</hi> nor perhaps of <hi>Credibility. pag.</hi> 59.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'The <hi>Athanaſians</hi> abhor Polytheiſm, no leſs than do the
<hi>Arians.</hi> If their Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſeem to infer it, they deny the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; if this
contradict the Rules of reaſoning, they avow it; for they allow Reaſon no hearing in
Myſteries of Faith: if this make them Hereticks, it is not in Religion, but in Logick.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'On the other ſide the <hi>Arians</hi> profeſs to believe of Chriſt
whatever himſelf, or his Apoſtles have ſpoken; and where one expreſſion in Scripture
ſeemeth to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict another, they take ſuch a Courſe to reconcile them, as the Laws and
Cuſtoms of all the World direct. It is very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent for Rhethorick to exceed, but never to
diminiſh the Grammatical Character of a Perſon, whoſe honour the Writer profeſſeth to
advance: and upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they think it more reaſonable, that thoſe Expreſſions which
exalt our Savior's Perſon to an Equality with the Father, ſhould ſtoop to thoſe which
ſpeak him In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior; than that thoſe which ſpeak him Inferior ſhould be ſtrained up to
thoſe which ſpeak him Equal. And however this is the ſafer Way; ſince it will lead us to
ſuch a Belief, as will ſuffice for that end, for whoſe ſake alone Belief it ſelf is
required. <hi>pag.</hi> 59. <hi>of the Interpolated Edition.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>To this Queſtion,</hi> Whether any promiſe of God does
neceſſarily import a reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame numerical matter?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>He anſwers,</hi> That the Words of St. Paul; <hi>Thou fool, that
which thou ſoweſt, &amp;c.</hi> plainly deny the Reſurrection of the ſame numerical
particles.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>To another Queſtion,</hi> Whether it be more honorable to God, and
more ſerviceable to the deſign of the Goſpel, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Contrary?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>He anſwers,</hi> That it is the ſame, as to ask, Whether it be
more honorable to ſalve all his Perfections, or to robb one that we may clothe the other.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this and the other two follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paragraphs, I anſwer, That they relate
to the Differences of thoſe Times, wherein the hot Biſhops on both ſides eagerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
with one another, to the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Detriment of the Church, and Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the Empire:
But wiſe and ſtay'd Men, ſuch as the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and thoſe Biſhops
that were his Counſellors, had ſuch an eſteem of thoſe Controverſies as our Author.</p>
            <p>But, 2. as to our Times, and the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, I ſee not
but that they who hold it ſo ſtiffly, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their Brethren on that ſcore, have no
mind to remove Occaſions of Difference and Separation, but to continue them; which one may be
tempted to believe they would not do, but for the ſake of, ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and baſe
Intereſt. See more in the Judgment of one of our moſt eminent Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſumming up that
Letter of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> which this Author preſſed. <hi>Infra</hi> p. 14.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50224:6"/>
            <p>This Perſecution of the Author of <hi>the Naked Goſpel,</hi> and the manner of it, is ſo
threatning, both to thoſe of the National Church, and the Diſſenters from her, that a fiercer
Perſecution may reaſonably be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected than any we have ſeen in the late Reigns. The Example
is clear in thoſe that being of the Church have any thing to loſe pertaining to it: And for
Diſſenters, the Burners, and other their Brethren, do well know that none of 'em can give
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, except ſome Presbyterians; and non-aſſent
let's looſe all the Penal Laws, hungry Chancellors, peeviſh or bigotted Juſtices, and
raſcally Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers againſt them. Is this the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that was promiſed? If it ſhould come
to this, How much worſe would the Proteſtant National Church of <hi>England</hi> deal with her
Children, than the Papal Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> This prohibits 'em to read the Bible, and ſo
prevents the occaſion of queſtioning her Doctrines: but that gives us the Scripture to read,
but will perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te us if we believe not, and profeſs more than, or contrary to what is therein
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd; contrary to the common Principle of Proteſtants, and moſt expreſly of this Church
her ſelf in her Sixth Article, which ſaith.
<q rend="margQuotes">'The Holy Scripture containeth all things neeeſſary to ſalvation,
ſo that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not read therein, nor can be proved thereby, is not to be required of
any one to to believed as an Article of Faith, or of neceſſity to Salvation.</q> If they do not
mean by <hi>[proved thereby]</hi> prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſatisfaction of every ſober Man, the Church of
<hi>Rome</hi> will prove all her Articles in the ſame way and manner.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I take the freedom of telling you my thoughts upon this occaſion; but now I muſt
return and ask you, whether the Learned Aſſembly of Burners have proved that the <hi>Naked
Goſpel</hi> does not only deny the Godhead of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but <hi>oſtentui
habet</hi> (as their Phraſe is) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him to ſcorn, or make a ſhew of him? Do all their
Exſcriptions prove any part of their horrid Charge?</p>
            <p>As for his denying the <hi>reſurrection of the ſame numerical Particles,</hi> you know, that
ſince the newer Philoſophy got Credit, that Doctrine is often taught in our Pulpits, and I am
inform'd even at St <hi>Mary</hi>'s in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> too, beſides in divers learned Mens
Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. Good God! when ſhall the Spirit of Perſecution be caſt out! when will
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans learn to be juſt as Men, not to ſay lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and tender-hearted as Brethren! They
boaſt of the truth of their Faith, but it is not ſuch as worketh by Love. What is it to honour
Chriſt in their Words, and diſhonour him in their Lives? Fourteen Hundred Years experience has
taught the World, that Men contend for Opinions and Speculations in Religion, for the gratification
of their Pride, Covetouſneſs, Revenge, and the like worldly Intereſts.</p>
            <p>Though my Letter has been ſo long, I'le venture ſtill to entertain you, Sir, with
ſomething conſiderable about Dr. <hi>Bury,</hi> the ſuppoſed Author of the <hi>Naked
Goſpel,</hi> of which I am credibly inform'd. To have a Book condemn'd long after 'twas printed,
nay, when its Author and his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg were ſtrugling againſt heavy Oppreſſion in their
Rights and Priviledges, will put the World upon enquiring into the Reaſons and Motives of ſuch
an Action, as well as the Life and Conduct of the Author. The Rector of <hi>Exeter</hi> Colledg
then (having done what lay in his Power for his King) was expell'd from his Fellowſhip, for
refuſing to ſubmit to the Viſitors in 1648, and the only Perſon who had courage to read the
Prayers of his then diſtreſs'd Mother the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Colledg, when
<hi>extempore</hi> Ones were in faſhion; for which he was led, by a Fileof Muſqueteers, to the
next Port, turn'd out, and forbid entrance again upon pain of Death; and he never after ran counter
to ſo good a beginning. Would not one think, Sir, this ſufficient to procure him the reſpect
and veneration of thoſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50224:7"/>who are his worſt Enemies? Had any of them fallen into Circumſtances leſs
trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, what out-cries, I ſancy, would there have been! what writing of Letters! what
trumpeting of Praiſes! what noiſe of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and paſt Sufferings! not a Figure in Rhetorick
but muſt have been drawn dry by one Wit or other; and had that fail'd, the World muſt have been
hector'd into a good Opinion. After he was made Rector, he never did any thing that look'd as if he
had forgot his firſt Loyal Principles, but led a quiet, ſober, and unblameable Life; given very
much to good Works, as may be prov'd by his Buildings in the Colledg; his large Contributions to
the Company for Relief of Clergy-mens Widows and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan; beſides other leſs viſible
Inſtances, not fit to be mentioned while he's alive: All which none indeed can deny that will not
baſely wrong him. He was ſo ſtrict an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of what he thought the Will of his Founder,
that he would have declar'd his own Son's Fellowſhip void, (ſtaying ſome time longer beyond
Sea than his Father thought allowable) if not prevented by the Fellows of his Colledg. He wrote a
Book call'd <hi>The Conſtant Communicant,</hi> dedicated to, and approv'd of by his Grace the
preſent Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> wherein he pleads the Authority of the Church as an
Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo to be. Thus far he's come, without the leaſt: ſuſpicion of want of Zeal for
the Church, on of Hereſy.</p>
            <p>But we won't ſecure him for the future; for the laſt Publick Act that was at
<hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> he expelled one of the <hi>Terrae Filius</hi>'s for being very abuſive to Dr.
<hi>Wallis,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſſing to deſiſt when commanded. This mightily diſpleas'd the
Junior Maſters, and he now finds they have not forgot him. In <hi>October</hi> laſt he joins
with the Senior Fellows to expel another of their Degree, (Mr. <hi>Colmer</hi>). Fellow of his own
Colledg, for Fornication; which though it has occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd him and his Colledg all their Troubles,
yet let us by no means ſay it made the <hi>Naked Goſpel</hi> Heretical and Impious. But
purſue Matter of Fact about the Manner of the Decree. After the Biſhop of <hi>E.</hi> had
viſited <hi>E.</hi> Colledg, contrary to their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and Proteſtation, the major part of
the Fellows ſuſpended for not betraying their Priviledges: One of them Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitated for the
heinous Crime of reading Prayers after that Suſpenſion; the Rector himſelf expell'd for
Contumacy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and excommunciated for not yielding up his Lodgings (as you have been
informed.) While they were ſeeking redreſs from her Majeſty and Privy Council, a Petition
againſt <hi>the Naked Goſpel</hi> ſubſcrib'd by Thirty or Forty of the Maſters, was
publickly and rudely preſented to Dr. <hi>M.</hi> Pro-Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, to be read in
Congregation: but he refuſed, and gave it to the Vice-chancellor. Now, pray, Sir, pleaſe to
obſerve, that this was an irregular way of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for the Vice-Chancellor only ought to
take notice of Matters of that Nature, and Petitions are not to be tendred by great Numbers.
However he gave way ſo far, as to call a meeting of the Heads of Houſes, where the Buſineſs
met with ſome oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it being freely ſaid, that it was not fit they ſhould be made
Tools for the Biſhop of <hi>E</hi>— or ſome ſuch thing; yet 'twas then referr'd to the
two Profeſſors, Dr. <hi>Jane</hi> (who drew up the famous Decree of 1683) and Dr.
<hi>Hall,</hi> barely to draw Propoſitions out of the Book: the latter declin'd it, and the
former is ſaid to have done it as in the Decree. In the mean time her Majeſty in Council is
moſt graciouſly pleaſed to order the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exeter</hi> ſhould put in an
Anſwer to the Rector and Fellows Petition, and to declare a Day ſhould be appointed for
hearing. May we not think this haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd the Decree?—But now the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſeeing
nothing done upon the former Petition, lay hold of a time when a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation was call'd, upon
another Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to deliver another Petition, in a yet more tumultuous manner, and with many
more Hands, to the Vice-Chancellor as he came out; who took it amiſs, and reprov'd
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50224:7"/>them, ſaying, <hi>He did not like that way of proceeding;</hi> yet it came at
laſt to what the World ſees. I ſhan't tell you, Sir, what manner of Men promoted it, you
eaſily by this time gueſs; and though the Univerſity ſeem to be very ſenſible of the
Figure they make in the World, and the Deference paid their Opinion: yet knowing that one of the
Profeſſors refus'd to be engag'd, and hearing that ſeveral Heads of Houſes, and others were
abſent when the Decree paſt; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering alſo the Time and Manner of it, and the ill Fate
of the now exploded Decree in 1683, That the <hi>N. G.</hi> (ſuppoſing Dr. <hi>B.</hi> the
Author) ought not to prejudice him in his juſt Rights, (which ſeems chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd) and
eſpecially his Colledg, who are nothing concern'd: that it's now no Secret who are the Engines
and Movers of all this, that his worſt Enimies live not far from a place where the Prayer has not
been uſed for his Majeſties ſucceſs in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (but juſt on Faſt-days when it
can't be help'd) no, nor that in time of War and Tumults; that conſidering the Time when ſome
things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, one may wiſh there was not ſome further uſe intended to be made of them,
than the ruining a Rector, and major part of a Colledg; (who are notoriouſly known to be as firm
and hearty for the preſent. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as any in the three Kingdoms); that the Univerſity are
not the proper Judges of Hereſy; that they have no Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute (as I can hear of) for burning of
Books: That the Author is abus'd in the Quotations; that he's only guilty of a large, generous, and
extenſive Charity, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Socinian</hi> nor <hi>Arian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſt of all, conſidering that ſeveral Perſons, of a Character above any of the
worthy Condemners, and no ways inferior to the beſt of them (if not exceeding) in Learning and
Wiſdom, have declared, that upon reading the Book they could not ſee any Hereſy in it: I
ſay, Sir, when one ſeriouſly reflects, and without prejudice, on all theſe things, one may
ver well afford to wiſh the Decree juſt as much <hi>Succeſs,</hi> as its Authors have ſhewn
<hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here it may not be amiſs, Sir, to oblige you with what hath been ſaid by an excellent
Prelate of our own Church; who has alſo ſumm'd up that <hi>celebrated Epiſtle</hi> of the
<hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Wiſe Conſtantine:</hi> which will be ſo entire a Vindication of the
Author of the <hi>Naked Goſpel,</hi> that nothing can be ſo much as whiſper'd againſt him;
and which Perſons of free and generous Minds may be apt to oppoſe to the Sentiments of the
Univerſity <hi>however conſiderable.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'There are ſome wiſe Perſons (ſays this great Man, ſpeaking of
the firſt Council of <hi>Nice</hi>) that think the Church had been more happy, if ſhe had not
been in ſome ſenſe conſtrain'd to alter the Simplicity of her Faith, and make it more
<hi>curious</hi> and <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate,</hi> ſo much that he had need be a <hi>ſubtile Man to
underſtand the words of the New Determinations.</hi> (And a little after.) Now then they that
liv'd in that Age, that underſtood the Men, that ſaw how quiet the Church was before this
ſtir, how miſerably rent now; <hi>what little benefit from the Queſtion, what Schiſm about
it,</hi> gave o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cenſures of the Buſineſs than we ſince have done, who only look on the
Article as determin'd with Truth and Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Church generally ſince that Time.
<hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>But the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of</hi> Conſtantine <hi>to</hi>
Alexander <hi>and</hi> Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <hi>tells the Truth, and chides them both for commenting the
Queſtion,</hi> Alexander <hi>for broaching it,</hi> Arius <hi>for taking it up; and although this
be true that it had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Church it never had begun; yet being begun,</hi> What is
to be done in it? Of this alſo in that <hi>admirable Epiſtle,</hi> we have the
<hi>Emperor</hi>'s <hi>Judgment,</hi> (I ſuppoſe not without the advice and privity of
<hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corduba,</hi> whom the Emperor lov'd and truſted much, and
employ'd in the delivery of the Letters).</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50224:8"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Firſt he calls it a certain vain piece of a Queſtion, ill begun,
and more unadviſedly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; a Queſtion which no Law, nor Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Canon
defineth; a fruitleſs Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the product of iile Brains, a Matter ſo</hi> nice,
<hi>ſo</hi> obſcure, <hi>ſo</hi> Intricate, <hi>that it was neither to be</hi> explicated by
the Clergy, <hi>nor</hi> underſtood by the People. <hi>A Diſpute of words, a Doctrine
inexplicable, but</hi> moſt dangerous when taught, <hi>leſt</hi> it introduce Diſcord or
Blaſphemy: <hi>And therefore the</hi> Objecter was raſh, <hi>and the</hi> Anſwerer
unadviſed; <hi>for it</hi> concerned not the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Faith, or the Worſhip of God, or
any chief Command of Scripture; <hi>and therefore why ſhould it be the Matter of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord? For
though the Matter be grave, yet becauſe neither Neceſſary nor Explicable, the</hi> Contention
is trifling and toyiſh: <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the Philoſophers of the ſame Sect, though
differing in the Explication of an Opinion, have yet more love for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the
Profeſſion, than diſagreement for the difference of Opinion. So ſhould Chriſtians,
believing in the ſame God, retaining the ſame Faith, having the ſame Hopes, oppoſed by the
ſame Enemies, not fall at variance upon ſuch Diſputes; conſidering</hi> our
Underſtandings are not all alike; <hi>and therefore neither can</hi> our Opinions in ſuch
myſterious Articles. <hi>So that the Matter being of</hi> no great Importance, <hi>but</hi> vain,
and a Toy <hi>in reſpect of the excellent</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings <hi>of</hi> Peace and Charity,
<hi>it were good that</hi> Alexander <hi>and</hi> Arius <hi>ſhould leave con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, keep their
Opinions to themſelves, ask each other forgiveneſs, and</hi> give mutual To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſubſtance of <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Letter, and it contains in it <hi>much
Reaſon,</hi> if he did not undervalue the Queſtion; but it ſeems it was not then thought
<hi>a Queſtion of Faith,</hi> but <hi>of Nicety of Diſpute:</hi> They both did believe one God,
and the Holy Trinity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But for the Article it ſelf, the Letter declares what
Opinion he had of <hi>that;</hi> and this Letter was by <hi>Socrates</hi> called, <hi>A Wonderful
Exhortation, full of Grace and ſober Counſels;</hi> and ſuch as <hi>Hoſius</hi> himſelf
who was the Meſſenger, preſſed with <hi>all earneſtneſs,</hi> with all the
<hi>Skill</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> he had. Thus far that Great and Learned Biſhop, <hi>Lib.
Propheſ. Sect.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>And now let all thoſe who are <hi>diſcreet</hi> and <hi>reaſonable,</hi> condemn that
<hi>truly great Emperor,</hi> our own <hi>Worthy Prelate,</hi> and the ingenuous and charitable
Author of <hi>the Naked Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am afraid I have drawn out this Account to a greater length than that the reading of it may
ſuit your little Leiſure, but I doubt not your Pardon to,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>R</hi>
               </salute>
               <signed>Your —</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 30. 1690.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50224:8"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THe Reader is deſired to take notice, that if the Sayings of the Fathers, and other eminent
Perſons, were to be quoted for that purpoſe, for which ſome of them are already mention'd,
they alone would fill a Volume, and perhaps as uſeful an One as any yet extant: But we ſhall
only trouble him with one very remarkable ſaying of <hi>Tertullian, Lib. de Velaud.
Virg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">'<hi>Regula quidem fidei,</hi> &amp;c. This Symbol (ſpeaking of the
Apoſtles <hi>Creed</hi>) is the One <hi>Sufficient, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nalterable</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable
Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> that admits no <hi>Encreaſe</hi> or <hi>Decreaſe;</hi> but if the
<hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of this be preſerved,</hi> in all other things Men may take
liberty of enlarging their Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Propheſyings, according as they are aſſiſted by
the Grace of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And with one Paſſage out of the <hi>Naked Goſpel,</hi> firſt Edition, <hi>pag.</hi> 73.
<hi>line</hi> 23.
<q rend="margQuotes">'The Author of the Goſpel is a <hi>Perſon,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>Great,</hi> but <hi>Infinite;</hi> and no leſs ſo in <hi>Power</hi> than
<hi>Faithfulneſs,</hi> ſo that there is no place for miſtruſt.</q> Though this has not been
mentiou'd in the, Letter, yet is it as plain as can be poſſible, and may be ſound in all the
Editions of the Book, and which ought ſure to be acknowledged by the <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,
Impartial,</hi> and Learned Condemners.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
